<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="Koncerak_sep_21_01_RNC.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root><title>Leaves</title>
    <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author>
    <born-died>1941 –</born-died>
    <stan>Every October it becomes important, no, necessary to see the leaves <device
            repeat="turning">turning, to be surrounded by leaves turning</device>; it's not just the
        symbolism, to confront in the death of the year your death, one blazing farewell appearance,
        though the irony isn't lost on you that nature is most seductive when it's about to <device
            repeat="die">die, flaunting the dazzle of its incipient exit, an ending that at least so
            far the effects of human progress (pollution, acid rain) have not yet frightened you
            enough to make you believe is real; that is, you know this ending is a deception because
            of course nature is always renewing itself— the trees don't die</device>, they just
        pretend, go out in style, and return in <device repeat="style">style: a new
        style</device>.</stan>
    <!--This entire first stanza is one sentence, which is why I found myself running out of breath reading it out loud-->
    <!--It's full of punctuation but never any that end the sentence-->
    <stan>Is it deliberate how <device repeat="far">far they make you go especially if you live in
            the city to get far</device> enough away from home to see not just <device
            repeat="trees">trees but only trees</device>? The boring highways, roadsigns, high
        speeds, 10-axle trucks passing you as if they were in an even greater hurry than you to look
        at leaves: so you drive in terror for literal hours and it looks like rain, or snow, but
        it's probably just clouds (too cloudy to see any color?) and you wonder, given the poverty
        of your memory, which road had the most color last year, but it doesn't matter since you're
            <device repeat="probably">probably too late anyway, or too early— whichever road you
            take will be the wrong one and you've probably</device> come all this way for
        nothing.</stan>
    <!--The second stanza is now two sentences compared to the first one's one -->
    <stan>You'll be driving along depressed when suddenly a cloud will move and the sun will muscle
        through and ignite the hills. It may not last. Probably won't last. But for a moment the
        whole world comes to. Wakes up. Proves it <device repeat="lives">lives. It lives</device>—
            <device tally="colors">red, yellow, orange, brown, russet, ocher, vermilion,
            gold</device>. <device repeat="Flame and rust">Flame and rust. Flame and rust</device>,
        the permutationsof burning. You're <device repeat="on fire">on fire. Your eyes are on
            fire</device>.It won't <device repeat="last">last, you don't want it to last</device>.
        You can't stand any more. But you don't want it to stop. It's what <device
            repeat="you've and you'll">you've come for. It's what you'll come back for. It won't
            stay with you, but you'll remember that it felt like nothing else you've</device> felt
        or something you've felt that also didn't last.</stan>
    <!--The last stanza is full of sentences, the complete opposite of the first stanza -->
    <IP>Copyright © 1992 by Lloyd Schwartz.</IP>
    <origin>From Goodnight, Gracie (The University of Chicago Press, 1992).</origin> Appears
    courtesy of the author.
</root>
